Organizations need to think beyond code
generation. There are so many aspects of
the SDLC that do not necessarily have to
do with just creating code. And the
organizations that are going to see the
biggest impact are the ones who are
getting really creative about the AI
code reviews. Right? So developer goes
and commits some code. Agent notices
that immediately analyzes the diff uses
maybe something like MCP to understand
the context of the change and then
provides immediate feedback. Deming is
famous for saying that 90 to 95% of the
productivity output of an organization
will be determined by the system and not
the worker. With AI in particular, the
DORA study shows, you know, things like
with a 25% increase in overall adoption
of these tools. Year ago, these tools
didn't work nearly as well as they do
now. And that's why a lot of people
being very very bullish. The hype around
these like 10x 100x improvements are
just that the data is not bearing that
out.
>> Everything must be AI or every company
needs to have something AI. every
product needs to have an AI feature.
We've almost lost sight of the should we
and jumped into the we must do this.
Given that, what's the true value if we
take it back to fundamentals of doing
this measurement?
>> It's such a good question.
[Music]
>> Hello, it's Simon Maple here and welcome
to another episode of the AI Native Dev.
And today we're going to be talking all
about um well, how good is AI for us?
and how can we measure it and how can we
actually make changes based on what
we're measuring. Joining me today is
Justin Rio and Justin is a deputy CTO at
DX. Justin, welcome. How are you?
>> Hey, Simon. Thanks for having me.
>> Oh, absolute pleasure. Where about you
calling in from today, Justin?
>> I'm in Columbia, South Carolina. My wife
and I moved here about seven months ago.
>> Oh, wow. How are you finding it?
>> You know what? It's a really underrated
town. It's a capital city. It's a
university city. There's a lot here. We
have the largest zoo in the US because
we combined it with a botanical garden.
Uh really good bars and restaurants and
and and culture. So we're uh between
both of our kids. We have grown kids in
Atlanta and Rally, North Carolina. So
we're kind of 3 hours from from either
one. So
>> amazing. I'm already learning something.
The big it's got so it's the biggest zoo
in the US.
>> Biggest zoo in the US, which is crazy.
Yeah. You wouldn't think that it's here,
but yeah, it's in terms of footprint.
>> Right. And tell us a little bit about
DX. Yeah. So, DX um was started by uh
Abby Nota uh who is a researcher uh and
who sold a company called Pull Panda to
uh GitHub ultimately Microsoft uh a few
years ago and has been you know really
an expert foremost researcher on
developer productivity and and developer
experience. uh and he teamed up with
Nicole Forsrren uh who published the
Dora metrics and and and sold Dora to
Google Cloud a number of years ago as
well as Margaret Anne Story who is the
primary author of the space framework
and you can kind of think of it as like
all of the research that's been done
through like the Microsoft productivity
research and university of uh uh British
Columbia uh in in uh Victoria all kind
of combined into a product that then
gathers data to try to measure developer
experience. And then the knock on
effects of better developer
productivity.
>> Interesting. And and so the company has
obviously been hugely based in this
space for a fair while. I think we last
time we talked it was was it 9 10 years
old?
>> Uh no no DX is going on four years.
>> Oh four years. Still a pretty new
company. Yeah.
>> So four years. So but but it was pre the
kind of like the big AI boom.
>> Oh for sure. Yeah. Yeah. All of this,
you know, the the theory and our our
measurement frameworks like the core 4
and the developer experience index all
yeah predate um kind of what's what's
happened over the last year or so with
with AI
>> and so and so kind of you know obviously
with talking about developer experience
and productivity and things like that in
and around the developer space and then
all of a sudden something like the the
big wave I think we mentioned it before
on offline the big wave of AI hits. Did
you get the oh moment like everyone
else where it's like hang on is this a
is this a a wind on our back or you know
a wind in our face? How does this affect
us?
>> No absolutely. I mean I think you know
it's fair to say that we're in that
heavy disruption phase now where we have
to kind of rethink a lot of you know
truths that we've been able to take for
granted in the industry for a while. Um,
I think that, you know, the the good
news for DX is that we've always been
measuring developer productivity and
developer experience. And that is still
the point of rolling out AI and AI
assistance and agents and things like
that, at least from a software
engineering perspective. I think um, you
know, it's easy to lose sight of that in
all the hype like why are we even doing
this? Why are you know, why is this so
critical for organizations? And it's
still about, you know, improving,
augmenting what developers can do and
and and by that sort of the developer
experience for the for the better
knock-on effect of of of productivity.
So
>> everything that we've been doing in
terms of measuring the impact of
developer experience on an organization,
measuring the various drivers that that
that sort of comprise what we would
define as developer experience, those
are still completely relevant, right? I
think that we just have to start, you
know, rethinking some of the the methods
that that are going to be used. We need
to start rethinking the role of a
developer a little bit. Um but in terms
of of how to measure the productivity of
an organization, I don't think that
that's changed fundamentally.
>> Yeah. And I and I guess thinking about
the um with AI in particular, I feel
like um that there's this kind of like
more of a long-term and a short-term
productivity, I guess. Uh so if we
reflect with another tool maybe an IDE
or something like that the an IDE will
provide me with the ability to speed up
how I'm going to do a task and I will
get to an end state quicker you know
with an IDE than without an ID typically
talking for myself and I you know I
think that's largely the case with most
people as well with AI of course um I
guess there's two different states one
is the can I get to a state whereby I
have some code that I could check in or
some code that will that will run and
and and perform some certain feature,
but is that then of a good enough
quality that longer term I'm not
actually spending more time in the
maintenance and other things. Um, so I
guess with AI there's probably a couple
of measures. One being that short-term
cannot how fast can I do this task and
then secondly more of that maintenance
the longer the longer term uh aspect of
is this actually helping me uh longer
term. What what's your kind of like take
on on the on that kind of assessment?
No, I mean I think you're you're spot
on. I think that, you know, we have a
number of metrics that we put together
in our our AR measurement framework,
which we can of course, you know, get
into in this conversation, but it really
does boil down to those two levers of
like velocity, quality and and and
maintainability, however you want to
call it, right? We we do have to be very
careful that these velocity gains that
we're clearly making now aren't just
trading technical debt down the road as
the code base becomes less maintainable
or as the code quality fails, right? So
we do have to really pay attention to
both of those things like are we, you
know, getting what we wanted out of this
investment as an organization in terms
of being able to augment crank up our
cap capabilities and are we hopefully
not just going to break things a year
from now and I think that for a lot of
organizations it's it is it is a
longitudinal impact that we're thinking
about like we we we you do have to
consider that we we may not really know
for for like a year you know with with
with with depending on how you know
quick we're cracking up changes to the
codebase which is something that you
know has become sort of a new bottleneck
is now sort of human oversight in the
process. We know that with this
additional velocity comes generally a
higher PR throughput more more PRs being
asked to emerge which means more
oversight. So I I think it is going to
take time for us to really understand
organization by organization these these
these long-term impacts. Um but it's
clearly speeding things up now. you
know, it's not the 100x improvements. I
I think that's a lot of uh uh
information that's very good for
creating YouTube subscribers and up
votes and stuff, but not necessarily uh
increased productivity for
organizations. But more realistically,
looking at numbers like 20, 25, 30%
increases in in velocity, I think is is
is a is a good number and and it's
certainly making an impact.
>> Yeah, I'd love to jump into the
framework in just a second.
very very keen on that. Uh I I'd love to
almost like bring it back a little bit
because I think you mentioned something
just a minute ago which was super super
interesting to me which is the fact that
people are almost like forgetting to to
to measure forgetting to even think
about measuring and and I feel like a
lot of that is because you know there's
this big wave of oh every everything
must be AI or every company's needs to
be needs to have something AI every
product needs to have an AI feature and
we've almost like lost sight of it lost
sight of the should we um and and and
jumped into the we must do this. Um
given that what's the why do we need to
measure? What's the what's the value in
in measuring something which we you know
potentially are naturally just wanting
to lean into anyway whether or not it's
perfect a 2x a 3x whatever uh percentage
what's the what's the true value if we
take it back to fundamentals of of doing
this measurement? I mean, it's such a
such a good question, right? I mean, I
think that there's multiple dimensions
that we really need to pay attention to
as we're rolling these things out. Uh, I
mean, you're you're right. I think that
the hype and the fact that I think maybe
even non-technical executives and
decision makers in certain organizations
like do sort of understand this
technology like they're using claude or
they're using chat GPT or something like
that. It's very different than the last
major hype cycle which was of course
cloud and you know with cloud you didn't
have a lot of non-technical leaders
talking about multicloud migration of
containerbased workloads I that wasn't
you know vernacular that was necessarily
understood um but now you do have you
know more nontechnical leaders and
decision makers who who do have a an
inkling of what this technology can can
do um and so because of that we have
this rush where it's like there's this
FOMO it's like oh my gosh if we're not
mandating AI in the organization or if
all of our developers aren't using AI,
we're going to fall behind. We're going
to lose our competitive edge. And you
know, there may be uh some truth to
that. But you don't know really unless
you're measuring, right? We we know that
there are some organizations who when
they actually start um you know putting
the sensors in place and and and running
the data, they're doing worse in in some
in some cases, right? We we saw that MER
study which was you know I think we we
need to take the results of that study
with a grain of salt uh given that it
was a relatively low sample size and
that the tasks wasn't weren't you
necessarily indicative of what people
are doing through the full SDLC but that
study provided some data that said that
a lot of developers are actually slowed
down right and and without measuring we
don't really know uh so these dimensions
that we need to look at you know I think
first of all we need to understand
utilization right okay we roll this out
especially large scaled engineering
organizations who's using it right uh
can we find differences in patterns
between uh engineers that are heavy
users of AI versus ones who aren't uh do
we know if this is uh more helpful for
junior developers or more helpful for
senior developers and right without you
know looking at the basic utilization
metrics we don't really have an
understanding of that and then we
already talked about quality we need to
understand the overall impact to of the
engineering organization quality is is
one of those impacts, right? Is is the
code m, you know, is it still
maintainable? Are we moving semantically
away from from the the norms that we
usually have in an organization which is
going to make the code harder to read or
you know not match what we like to do
with our with our culture. Uh and also
are we speeding up like are we seeing
more PRs coming through? are we, you
know, um, actually is our rate of
delivery going up as a result of of
these investments that we're making in
these tools and ultimately we will
eventually need to look at cost too,
right? I mean, in an organization, how
much are we investing and are we
actually seeing the right return on
investment? Um, we may get to a point a
year from now where, you know, it's it's
almost like a marketing cost. It's like
you want to to spend money on AI because
that spend will provably lead to better
outcomes for the for for the
organization as a whole. But I don't
think that we know that universally yet,
right? I think that that's still yet to
be seen. And without data, without
metrics, we really don't know which
direction we're heading in.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's absolutely those
metrics that determine to what extent we
we bet and to how much we invest in
those in those types of things. Um yeah,
love the answer. Um let's talk about the
AI measurement framework then which is a
framework that that that you and some
other folks kind of like created in and
around um I guess everything from
whether it's as far as agents all the
way back down to kind of the the the
original code completion that that swept
us a number of years ago. Um first of
all I guess who came up with it and and
how did you come out with the uh with
the measurement framework? So, it's
primarily our CTO in Europe, Laura Taco,
who I'm sure a lot of you are familiar
with. She's very prolific and and
publishes a lot of great research, as
well as Abby, um, our CEO co-founder.
Uh, I I put my two cents in as well. It
was kind of a feverishly developed I
would say over about a 96-hour period
and then we validated it first against
data that we already had in the platform
uh from from uh metrics that were
already coming in around AI tool usage
uh and now we've had uh you know a
number of companies uh start start using
this framework like booking.com and
intercom um but we realized that you
know we have obviously I think the
biggest right to play in terms terms of
measuring this impact on productivity
because it's been the full focus of our
company uh and we've you know validated
our existing measurement frameworks like
the DX core 4 and the DXI across
millions of data points and hundreds of
companies at this point. So I think we
were already sort of best suited to do
this. It was just to your point earlier
we had an oh moment where like oh
my gosh we we need to put something out
there. Companies need to be able to
measure this stuff. So let's take what
we've learned uh from our existing
frameworks and and and the metrics that
actually can be used to drive decision-m
in an organization and can be used to
improve you know the the efficacy of an
engineering organization. Let's create
something complimentary
uh which can be used specifically to
look at the uh the impact that AI is
having uh within an organization. So we
we took the same uh sort of approach
that we took with the core 4 which is uh
for for those who may not be familiar
with core 4 it's sort of this
distillation of the three top uh
productivity metric frameworks out
there. So Dora uh space framework and
then the DevX framework. All three of
those are sort of rolled into one uh
metric framework and we take individual
metrics and we map them to specific
dimensions. Uh so that's like
effectiveness and quality um and and and
impact in in the case of the core 4 we
use the dimensions uh for our AI
measurement framework of utilization uh
impact and ultimately cost and and those
are in order right uh those kind of the
order that we recommend that you start
looking at things within the
organization first of all just
understand who's using the tool you know
daily active users weekly active users
within the organization
and then start measuring, you know,
which which contributions to the
codebase are actually AI assisted. And
there's a number of different ways that
you can do that. Probably the easiest
way is just to do some experience
sampling while pull requests are being
entered. Just have a little box that
says, "Yes, I used AI to help me with
this." Um, ultimately, we want to look
at percentage of committed code that's
AI generated. Um, that's a tougher
metric to grab. Um, but there's
different ways that it can be done, like
looking at the file system, for
instance. Um but we want to understand
you know is 20% of the code that's
actually making it into production uh is
was it AI generated and ultimately now
that everything's sort of moved past
just code assistance and autocomplete to
more agentic stuff throughout the SDLC
we want to understand how many actual
tasks have been assigned to agents uh
versus humans right so this is the first
step in in in sort of maturity around
measurement just understanding that that
aspect of who's using it
>> and I that's very very interesting and I
think with those three that you just
mentioned as well. So one one is kind of
like I guess more more around the
adoption or usage um you can get some
absolute around that I guess um probably
it's a little bit harder to kind of work
out when a developer is not using versus
using and how much of their their their
development is done with AI and like you
say how much of your development uh for
this pull request was AI assisted or
not. But it's it's kind of like more
concrete. I think the second the third
one that you mentioned as well, the
cost. Again, it's another concrete uh
thing. We have we have an absolute cost
at the end of it. I think the impact one
though is is really really tough to be
able to to kind of like decide. What
what do you um what what do you measure
in terms of impact or or what what
things do you measure that you know
categorize within the impact uh scope?
>> Yeah. So the again the good news for DX
is that this is still all about
developer productivity. So our
overarching metrics that have been part
of the core 4 are still essential to the
way that we look at impact. Now the DXI
has 14 different drivers uh that we look
at. Uh but that's just one part of the
core four which is our effectiveness
metric. Um so the core four metrics that
still matter that are still part of
impact that we want to look at are
things like PR throughput measuring our
velocity as well as our perceived rate
of delivery. uh the developer experience
index. Although I I I think and predict
that we will see some of those drivers
uh realign to how much AI is being used
in the organization or used per
individual developer. Um the quality
metrics, code maintainability, change
confidence, right? Do we think do we
have this feeling that we're going to be
breaking more stuff uh when we accept
code that was created by an agent or by
you know autocomplete? And then change
fail percentage. Look, that's a great
metric for quality. It's been a reliable
metric that that has served us well
through Dora and we still look at that
as our primary quality metric. But we
also have to look at like developer
satisfaction with these tools, right? We
should be looking at, you know, is this
something that developers feel is
actually making their experience better
because we've seen big differences
there, right? I don't want to pick on
any particular vendor, but like we've
seen overwhelming uh um uh positive
satisfaction with tools like cursor for
instance um that developers just
generally like it right and so we need
to understand is this something that's
actually making their experience better
or are we in some organizational culture
where we're mandating use of something
that developers actually don't like.
Right? that's very important uh to um
you know to to providing better
throughput for the organization by
creating a better developer experience.
Um, we want to look at time savings,
right? So, you know, how how many hours
a week, you know, whatever are being
returned to to developers, but we also
need to look at what they're working on,
right? Just because you've returned
time, uh, doesn't mean that that time is
necessarily going to be used to maybe
work on new features or things that
actually augment the overall
productivity of the organization. And we
want to understand, you know, human
equivalent hours of work that's been
completed by agents because that's
something that's going to inform whether
we're getting the right type of return,
whether uh whether we're enabling our
engineers to use the technology the
right way because you can't just expect
to just turn it on and everyone will
just magically know the best prompting
practices and the highest value use
cases and things. That's something that
has to be enabled in the organization as
well. So, you know, to to kind of sum
that up, I mean, we're looking at some
of the same metrics that we've always
been looking at, uh, because this still
is about better productivity, better
experience, but we also need to look at,
uh, some metrics that are specific to
the way that engineers feel about the
tool, like overall satisfaction as well
as how that's actually impacting their
time savings. And we know, you know,
that that software engineering and the
process of creating software goes well
beyond just writing code, right? I mean
even the the most recent Dora study that
came out uh talked about you know how
much time engineers actually have in
large scaled organizations to sit down
and write code it's like five or six
hours a week right so we have to be
thinking beyond just code generation in
terms of overall impact
>> yeah and and I really love the the mix
really between the as you say like the
what's the speed at which someone can go
what's the productivity gains that's
something like AI can provide a a
developer but it doesn't it it shouldn't
stop there Right. It should it should
include that sentiment that you that you
strive for as well, which I I guess
leans into the um experience, the
developer experience piece, which isn't
just can I achieve this velocity
increase with using AI. It's actually is
this a pleasurable experience? Is this
an experience that I'm enjoying coming
to my desk and and and building? Because
this is ultimately the new the new
department, the new the new role that
we're creating, that we're that we're
evolving to. And it does need to be one
of those roles that is enjoyable for
development because, you know, we want
people to to continue to to to to have
that career in software development and
it's it's core uh to that experience. Um
so I love I love the fact that you kind
of mix those two uh which is which is
super super important. Um for for people
who are listening where they think you
know what I agree with everything that's
being said. I love I love what you're
what you're saying and actually this is
something that I would love to do
myself. Um, it does seem kind of like a
a pretty uh a pretty deep integration
with with I guess not just developers
but with the system as well. How easy is
it to to be able to um come in from
scratch and say look I want to start
measuring all these things. um what do I
how long will it take me to actually get
these integrations, get everything
installed such that I can start pulling
this data and then I guess secondly, how
long do I need to wait before I can
actually get some kind of meaningful uh
measurement based on how well my teams
are performing with and without AI?
>> Yeah, it's a great question. I mean, and
it depends on which of these metrics
we're we're looking at, right? I mean I
I think uh we're very intentional about
these dimensions kind of being done in
order as almost like a maturity scale of
how well you're measuring. So looking at
utilization first then impact and then
ultimately cost. And that mirrors kind
of what we saw with cloud as well. I
mean it's amazing that you still see
brand new companies brand new companies
starting up that will help you measure
your cloud costs. and we're how long
into you know the cloud at this point
and I think you you'll see probably a
faster hype cycle with AI but you'll see
the same thing right we're going to just
who's using this we just got to roll
this out we got to get this in front of
all of our engineers and now we have to
start thinking about okay what have we
done and what is the impact of that and
then cost will be something that we need
to look at later um in terms of how we
measure and how long it takes to start
getting uh good data again it depends
right we're we want to think about
telemetry metrics, but those are
imperfect metrics, right? Those system
metrics that we can pull from, you know,
co-pilot API or cursors API or any of
these, you know, that's that's been, you
know, these tools are now working on
being able to expose and provide better
metrics. Um, but those metrics are are
often sort of incomplete.
They rely on things that don't
necessarily match reality. So for
instance, you know, the big popular one
with Copilot is like suggested lines of
code versus accepted lines of code. The
problem there is that the engineer
actually has to click accept in the IDE
for the API to know uh that those
numbers are are what they are, which
doesn't always happen, right? Sometimes
the suggestion will show up and oh
that's a good idea and then we'll just
type, you know, keep typing the code or
maybe we'll even copy paste without
clicking the accept button. Mhm.
>> So, you know, we we've sort of always
said that that system metrics are are
important uh and they are some of the
easiest metrics to gather, but they lack
a full context, right? So, a lot of DX's
philosophy is blending what we would
call qualitative or self-reported
metrics with the more quantitative
metrics that can come out of systems.
And we measure that using surveys. Uh we
measure that using self-reported data.
Now, when we think about a survey and we
think about an effective survey, we're
thinking about surveys that have 90 95
plus participation rates throughout the
organization, which is difficult to
achieve. We spend
>> and are those are those survey questions
in line in those actions or is that a
separate kind of like survey that gets
sent out to to folks within the
organization?
>> Yeah, so the the broader surveys are
separate, right? they're sent out. Uh
they take, you know, five minutes or so
for an engineer to complete. Um and you
know, we look at this sort of
three-legged stool. Like first of all,
you have to design really effective
surveys. And part of that starts with
understanding that you're not really
asking about um individual aspects.
You're actually asking more about the
system, right? We think about developer
experience as solving a systems problem,
not a people problem, right? Because I
mean look at Edwards Deming and
statistical process control or
everything that we learned from Ellie
Gold route and the theory of constraints
right Deming is famous for saying that
90 to 95% of the productivity output of
an organization will be determined by
the system and not the worker right so
we need to divi like design survey
questions that ask really good questions
about how the system is performing how
the platform is performing how the
culture is performing how the surrounded
processes are are performing when we
think about you know doing that type of
surveying but experience ience sampling
which is different that can be done sort
of more in the moment right this is
where okay we're adding a new um you
know a new question to our PR form did
you use AI to help perform this task
right then we can get some utilization
stuff that's coming in sort of real time
um so it's really hard to design a
highly effective survey and and because
of that I think a lot of engineering
organizations have a hard time getting
the type of uh participation rates that
can provide, you know, really actionable
data. But that doesn't mean you should
quit. Like you should try harder. You
should try to design surveys that uh
engineers actually get excited to take
part in because they understand that
it's providing a voice. They understand
that the data coming out of that survey
is actually going to be used uh to make
decisions about what to improve in the
platform and what to improve in the
overall developer experience. And if you
do that, if you go into it with that
mindset and you're diligent, you can run
highly effective surveys to the point
where we actually recommend, you know,
if the if you see some conflict, right?
If a system metric coming in seems to
conflict with what you're seeing from
the survey metrics, you should trust the
survey metrics and figure out why the
system metrics uh aren't aligning.
There's probably something wrong in the
way you're scraping the data or
something stale about the data. Um, so
so you want to measure from from
multiple angles, right? You definitely
want to pull system metrics where you
can, but you need to understand that
those system metrics are not going to be
your silver bullet metrics. They're not
going to tell you a complete story. You
also want to find a really good way to
get self-reported data in and then
correlate those things together. Um, you
know, utilization metrics can help you
on day one, right? You'll be able to
see, okay, you know, which users are are
are just straight up using these tools,
like are they, you know, are they
prompting? And regardless of the number
of accepted versus suggested or any of
that, just the raw data on who's using
these tools is something that you can
get actionable information on almost
immediately. These more longitudinal
metrics of code maintainability, change
confidence, change fill percentage. It's
going to take a little while uh to start
aggregating and looking at the right
trends to understand, okay, are things
getting better or are things getting
worse. Um but there's not, you know, one
single answer there. There's stuff that
you're going to be able to, you know,
get useful information on from day one.
Other things that you're going to have
to look at, uh, trends over time before
you really understand. And those those
are more of the impact metrics.
>> And and whenever whenever we think about
metrics, I think we all fairly well know
or I think it's worth pointing out that
it's it's always good to kind of like
really only largely compare against
yourself to some extent. uh whereby you
know whatever it is we should look at
ourselves and go okay this is where we
are right now as a baseline is there
areas we can improve is there areas that
are that you know surprise us and we
need to kind of like dig in and try and
work out because I think every
organization is different and so as a
result it it's hard to make those
comparisons that said uh I know you
there is an amount of benchmarking data
that is available whereby you can almost
compare what you what your uh what your
data h you
is showing you against I guess more
industry standard industry averages. Um
and as well as that of course there is
some um various companies and
organizations that share some of the
data that they've that they've extracted
from this uh this framework. Why don't
we why don't we start with the
benchmarks and then kind of like jump uh
to to maybe some more of the specifics
uh that folks have uh have shared. um
what are some of the benchmarks uh
telling us in and around I guess for me
adoption is kind of interesting but I'd
love to jump into into the the the
impact straight away what is what what
is some of the data sharing about maybe
developer impact with us being able to
uh use AI within our software process
for us to be able to you know ship and
deliver uh and create code that we can
kind of like you know deliver features
and things like that faster. what is the
data telling us?
>> Yeah, it's a great question. So, we
we've always uh provided sort of
industry benchmarks alongside uh the
productivity metrics that we have to try
to give, you know, um uh goals for
continuous improvement, but also to
provide a lever, you know, for an
organization to build a culture uh at
the level of maturity that they that
they want to build it, right? I mean,
depending on the organization, to your
point, all organizations are very
different. Um, maybe the the P50, so
50th percentile in the in the industry
is good for you. That's that's what you
want to hit. You feel comfortable there.
If you want to build like the highest
performing engineering teams in the
world, you're going to start looking at
the P90 metrics. You want to figure out
what the 90th percentile looks like in
terms of u how well they're performing
with these metrics. Um I mean we all
want to be the best but like at at what
level do we need to really put in that
effort um to be able to create software
effectively again depending on the
culture of our organization. So we look
at P50, P75 and P90 and we break that
across you know tech companies versus
non- tech companies and then it can even
get more granular like okay financial
services companies and things like that
so that we're not just providing a
platform where uh people can measure uh
uh the impact of their you know
developer experience on on productivity
but they can actually say okay well you
know maybe with this particular driver
in the DXI so maybe like documentation
or code maintainability
it turns out that we're 20 points
behind, you know, the industry P50 or
we're 10 points behind the the industry
P75. And so that that gives people a
goal to say, okay, well, what can we do?
What should we prioritize uh in terms of
making improvements to our process,
making improvements to our platform that
can drive us to um that kind of next
benchmark? With AI in particular though,
things are all over the place. I mean,
uh, the Dora study that came out and,
um, just a few months ago now, they
actually, if you go to the Dora
community website, you can download
their AI impact reports, very good data,
and it shows, you know, things like with
a 25%
increase in overall adoption of these
tools. We see things like um, you know,
7.5%
uh, improvement in overall code
documentation, but that was the highest
number in that study. 7 7.5% improvement
uh with a 25% overall adoption. Um all
of the results were positive in that
study, but there were low percentages
for some of these like 2 or 3%
improvements industrywide. Now things
are changing rapidly, right? I mean a
year ago, these tools didn't work nearly
as well as they do now. And that's why I
think you've seen the sort of seis
seismic shift around a lot of skepticism
to now a lot of people being very very
bullish. Um we have public data that
intercom um one of our customers
achieved a 41%
increase in AIdriven developer time
savings. Um which these are the these
are the right numbers to sort of expect
right now. You know again the hype
around these like 10x 100x improvements
are just that the data is not bearing
that out. Um but a 40% increase I mean
sure we'll take that. You know that's
great. And of course, intercom, we've
had Dez Trainer, for example, the
co-founder of Intercom on on the show
and also presenting at uh at at the uh
the DevCon uh AI Devcon. And Intercom is
such an AI first company in and around
not just the way that they're building
Finn their their um their tool, but just
the way they're using AI internally. I
think it it it's they're so driven to to
make the most of AI. Those numbers
almost don't shock me given the given
the the rate at which they're they're
they're adapting to use AI in their in
their methodologies. I
>> I think it's really you you raise a very
important point that and organizations
need to think beyond code generation,
right? There are so many aspects of the
SDLC that do not necessarily have to do
with just creating code and the
organizations that are going to see the
biggest impact are the ones who are
getting really creative about you know
maybe AI code reviews right that's a
great pattern right uh get an always on
you know agent that can give immediate
feedback about the code uh whether it's
one of these off-the-shelf uh solutions
uh like code rabbit or something like
that or whether you're just building the
stuff into your own platform which other
organizations are definitely doing.
They're just self-hosting a model or
they're using a an existing GBT API or
something like that, but then building
that into um the actual SDLC process. So
developer goes and commits some code
agent notices that immediately you know
analyzes the diff, uses maybe something
like MCP to understand the context of
the change and then provides immediate
feedback whether directly in the PR
comments or even providing code comments
or something like that, right? um that
can have a profound impact. We know that
you know code review and waiting on
review is a huge source of context
switching uh for engineers. It's
something that can really slow them
down. Uh so to be able to get that sort
of immediate feedback is great. Same
with documentation, right? I think it's
very interesting that the Dora study
showed us that the biggest gain was
actually in overall improvement of
documentation.
But it also shouldn't be too surprising,
right? I mean, most certainly not all,
but most engineers are not crazy about
having to document what they've done.
It's it's a step that is maybe not the
type of work that they really enjoy
doing. So, being able to have something
where an agent provides uh a draft uh of
of of documentation for the change or
again even better inline comments to
make the code more readable down the
line um is something that can absolutely
be a timesaver and increase the over
overall throughput of the organization.
Um we're even seeing you know uh
traditional non-technical or I say maybe
maybe non-builders
in the organization now empowered to uh
create you know lowrisk code
applications. So technical product
managers or folks that are close to the
project itself but maybe haven't been
able to you know write code in the past
they they can now do this. So we've seen
some organizations that are, you know,
allowing that to occur for like API
layer stuff, plugins, you know, things
that are that are relatively sort of low
risk and that's that's increasing the
overall throughput of the organization
as well. Um, so we've seen PRDs
generated from customer feedback where
you know that first stage of of planning
now is actually being offloaded to an
agent. So I think that that that is
where you'll see the most impact is
really being thoughtful and even
creative about the various aspects of
the SDLC that could be improved. Um and
to just you know really sit down and and
critically think about that like where
are our actual bottlenecks you know and
can an agent or some AI solution
actually help us there. Uh I think we we
should just never forget these early
principles of you know Ellie Goldroad if
you're not improving something that's
related to the constraint then you're
not actually going to see any downstream
improvements right I mean if you can if
you identify your bottlenecks uh in your
overall throughput and then your SDLC
and you're thoughtful about you know how
an agentic or some other type of
solution can help with that bottleneck
you'll see very positive results if
you're overindexing on something like
code generation which for a lot of
organizations is not the primary
bottleneck, then you need to expect, you
know, lower results. So,
>> yeah. Yeah. And I think that's
interesting when you talk about I mean
we I think you mentioned maturity a
couple of times and I always hate
talking about maturity when it comes to
AI just because I guess it's been such a
short runway anyway that we're that
we're grabbing uh AI and I don't know if
anyone's truly mature right now but it
but it is it is um really important to
kind of like identify which areas other
people are are looking into that we're
perhaps you know less mature or haven't
haven't really started looking into
those kind of areas. And I think you're
spot on because um a lot of the aspects
of the SDLC we you know when we think
about what are we doing with AI today a
lot of people will say well we're using
cursor or we're using something which is
a very predictable uh tool or or or
space to actually use AI and and and it
is interesting that actually a lot of
the processes that can either be
automated or or using AI to assist us
not necessarily you know creating huge
numbers of pull requests or or or or or
helping us write code line by line, but
it's actually all that all those other
things like you mentioned. I'm going to
pull some data for you here, some
relevant data so that you don't actually
need to look through all these things.
I've I've pulled all the information
into the pull request for you so you can
make a decision and you can validate uh
what I've what I've suggested in terms
of what people are doing to automate
those various areas. I guess first of
all, what are the typical places that
you see most um
most ignored or or or areas that you
feel most people can get, you know,
quicker gains that maybe they're not
thinking about straight away? And and
what are the things that people are
typically doing to make the biggest
productivity or or or developer
experience gains in those particular
areas? maybe even thinking things like
whether it's coding or documentation or
reviewing that you've kind of like
alluded to. What are the specifics that
people can actually do?
>> Yeah. So, another great question. I I
think um the the the one word that I can
use to to sum all that up is enablement,
right? That that's really being missed
by a lot of organizations. We um we set
out to kind of study this back in April
uh where we were seeing again I
mentioned before these results that are
like all over the place, right? Just
unevenly distributed, whatever you want
to call it. Some organizations clearly
feeling like they're seeing positive
outcomes from this, other organizations
not really sure or or even feeling like
they might be uh seeing negative
outcomes. And so um I put a study
together where we published into this
guide that we have published now on our
website the guide to AI assisted
engineering where I interviewed a lot of
like S-level so senior level uh
leadership um as well as broad surveys
of of engineers who were reporting uh
like good positive time savings. I I
wanted to see what was different
>> in these cultures, you know, and it
really came down to how engineers were
being enabled to use to use the uh the
tools from both a prompting best
practices standpoint. So, understanding
things like metaprompting and multi-shot
prompting, understanding how to take
advantage of of being able to manipulate
a system prompt or cursor calls them
cursor rules, understanding how
temperature is going to affect uh the
outcome of the way that you're doing
your prompting. um and understanding how
you're going to feed the right context
uh to these models. And then with a
broad survey of engineers, it was okay,
please stack rank what you think, you
know, your top five uh use cases, most
time-saving use cases are uh for using
some of these tools. And it was really
interesting that that the top one that
came out of that uh broad study was um
uh stack trace analysis, which is not
even a generative use case. um that was
eye opening for me as as somebody who's
an OG developer writing code uh
professionally since the the late '9s um
to to understand like and and Java code
for for that matter you just get used to
okay stack trace build fails I'm going
to go line by line I'm going to figure
out what went wrong with this but if you
allow the uh the the assistant or
whatever to do that explanation for you
you really do save a lot of time right
so um enablement is is kind of the first
thing that I would say there. Um I think
that uh that that then brainstorming and
planning. Uh so you've probably seen
some version of this workflow now where
it's uh I'm a project manager and you're
a senior React architect. You ask me one
question at a time about this problem
that I'm trying to solve. and the the
assistant or the agent will do a really
good comprehensive job of making sure
that you're pre-planning before you've
even started to write code is is pretty
bulletproof that you've considered all
those aspects of planning. I mean, I
don't know about I I always forget
something, you know, when I'm thinking
in that early pre-planning, you know, I
I don't think I missed some aspect of
what I should be doing with the data
schema or high availability or fault
tolerance or whatever it is. and and and
these things will remind you. Uh and
then you can literally turn around and
like copy that whole ch chat transcript
into like a reasoning model and say,
"Okay, now take this conversation that
we just had and break this into
individual units of work, even with with
prompting examples that I could use
later." You don't have to stop there.
You can take that specification and feed
it to a code generating model to
scaffold your entire project for you.
So, there's a lot of time savings that
can be gained in that early
brainstorming and planning process. It's
actually one of my favorite workflows
that I've tried to be a little bit more
reflexive about in terms of my my own
use. Uh and then certainly
documentation,
um pre-code review, right? These are
really good use cases uh that can uh
help unstick other bottlenecks in your
process. But I'd go back to what I said
said before like understand your
individual engineering culture first.
Understand your value stream, right? Do
that. I think uh you made a really good
point about maturity, you know, and that
it's it's that yes, things are moving at
at speed of light right now. Um but uh
it's still relatively nent. We're still
figuring out the best ways to do that.
But I would actually take that one step
further and I would say we still haven't
matured around developer productivity
and developer experience. Right? We've
worked really really hard to get a lot
of thought leadership out there and a
lot of research out there to help
organizations understand what developer
experience really means
>> and how that impacts the overall
productivity of an organization. But we
have not matured around it. There's not
a common language for it. You ask 10
different leaders and you probably still
will get 10 different answers about this
and then we just fast forwarded to AI
without really solving that initial
problem, right? And so I think like this
is why you know again the measurement is
still so important. This is why we we we
don't need we can't lose sight of those
conversations around what developer
experience means, what a good developer
experience looks like and how that
impacts our overall value stream. Right?
So um so I think you know there are
these aspects that we're learning, we're
getting creative about and there's
definitely you know common use cases,
best practices, best prompting
techniques, uh highv value use cases
that everyone should align around as
part of that maturity. But let's not
forget that we still haven't solved for
the greater problem of measuring and
understanding and improving developer
productivity with or without AI.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And I think there's levels
of AI as well of how we're going to be
using AI in our software development
whereby, you know, today the SDLC looks
kind of like a still fairly traditional
SDLC um whereby AI is working more as an
assistant to us. How's that SDLC going
to change perhaps as we lean more into
specs or uh AI agentic AI takes more of
the of the heavy lifting? Um there are
so many bigger changes uh it's going to
affect productivity and the the
experience of our development uh so
much. I think there are so many steps to
go. Really looking forward to see how
this evolves. Um Justin, for those folks
who were uh were are interested in, you
know, testing this out, uh learning
more, where where would you say is the
best place for someone to start?
>> Well, of course, I'm biased, but I would
say start with the research that that
we've already done. Uh we do publish a
lot of public research on this. Our our
impact framework is is if you go to our
website, getdx.com, you right now the
banner header on the website is check
out the AI measurement framework. So we
have a long white paper uh where we
detail these these metrics that I
mentioned before the different
dimensions that we place them into. Uh
we also have a survey template that's
available uh for measuring AI impact uh
alongside uh this measurement framework
which you can pull. Um so I would of
course say uh start with the research
that we produced. Uh it's all there for
you. It's all free. um and you can uh
start, you know, putting some of these
survey questions, some of these
experience sampling techniques in place
today and start gathering um some of
this data. Um I would think, you know,
again, you you really want to make sure
that you understand what you're
measuring. Uh and more importantly,
who's going to use this data, right? Um
that's a question that that often people
skip past, whether we're talking about
AI measurement or we're talking about
just overall measurement of developer
productivity. my good uh friend Max
Canad Alexander who uh ran developer
experience at Google and then uh
published the developer productivity and
happiness framework at LinkedIn and uh
now is at Capital One helping them with
the developer experience. He taught me
that in many ways the audience is more
important than the data. Right? If you
can't comfortably say
>> who's going to be upset if this data is
not available or even paralyzed because
they're using this to drive their own
decision-making in the organization, if
you can't comfortably answer who that
role is, then you may as well not even
capture the data in the first place.
Then you're just going to have this
dashboard that nobody uses, right? So I
would say start, you know, by thinking
about, okay, who's going to be the
recipient of this data? what decisions
uh is that going to inform? Then that
will help guide you to the data points
that are actually going to matter for
your culture and your organization. Then
it's a matter of do we get this from the
system metric? Do we get this from
experience sampling? Do we get this from
a from a survey? Figure out what's going
to be kind of most effective. Uh don't
overindex on a single metric ever,
right? That that hasn't changed. Um it's
so easy when we are only looking at one
metric like PR throughput or something
like that or or uh you know code
percentage of code generated by AI. If
we start really uh incentivizing
um based on those metrics or weaponizing
based on those metrics for that matter
then our old friend goodart's law comes
into effect immediately. We start
figuring out ways to game the system but
we're not actually improving our overall
productivity. the textbook one with PR
throughput has always been like oh I
have to get 10 10 PRs a week great I'll
update the read me file 10 times on
Monday and I'm done right you know and
but I haven't actually contributed
anything of value right so identify the
audience and then uh think about the
decisions that they need to make that
will help you move towards which metrics
plural are important to start looking at
uh so that we can understand the
tensions uh between those metrics um and
then we'll we'll ultimately use those
metrics to drive better decision
decision making uh but so yeah we have
lots of research uh we have a whole
white paper around this metric framework
that we've been talking about we have
survey templates ready to go uh just
load them up in Google forms and start
you know uh start start running them
within your organization and that's
that's a great start um but you know
continue to be vigilant you know
continue to be thoughtful about which
metrics are going to matter the most for
your culture uh and and don't uh cut
corners um you know make sure that
you're pulling not just system metrics,
not just telemetry, but also the
qualitative data that provides context
for that telemetry.
>> Yeah, such top advice because I feel
like that, you know, completely changes
the way you go about this entire
measurements journey. So, so important
to to to learn that from the start and
then build everything uh from those from
those decisions. So, um so yeah, so
getdx.com was it did you say or do
>> getdx.com? That's right.
>> getx.com. Awesome, Justin. Absolute
pleasure. We could probably talk for
another hour or so quite
>> certainly.
>> Really really appreciate your insights.
Um and uh and really looking forward to
hearing what our listeners think of uh
of of of the framework and it'll be
great to hear you know how people get on
if people want to reach out to you.
What's the best way of uh reaching
Justin?
>> Uh LinkedIn probably that's where I do
most of my stuff now. I was on that old
uh X for a while and things changed.
>> I've heard of it. I've heard of it.
Yeah. Yeah. Awesome. So, so yeah, catch
catch Justin on uh on LinkedIn then.
Really really pleasure chatting with you
on uh on today's episode. Um thanks very
much for all the insights, Justin.
>> Thanks so much, Simon. Had a great time.
>> Wonderful. And thanks everyone for uh
for tuning in. Um hope you enjoyed that
session and looking forward to uh to to
to another episode. Speak soon.